Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf officially is כ"ו,
Chaf-Vav, but we are going to, we'll be about an עמוד amud
behind. We pick up at the bottom of כ"ה עמוד א', Chaf-He
Amud Aleph, and we talked about various things people can do, you
know, in שול. shul. We sort of have been moving around issues
of reading the מגילה, Megillah, so קריאת התורה Kriyat HaTorah is a
central theme, but we've been discussing other issues as well. ברכת כהנים,
Birchas Kohanim, who gets various כיבודים, kibbudim, various things people can do
during דאווענינג, davening, which should be inappropriate in terms of dress and
words. But the last part of the last משנה Mishnah was about
inappropriate ways to translate certain verses, to do the תרגום, Targum, and
this משנה Mishnah is going to continue on the focus of reading
and תרגום. Targum. So let's take a look. מעשה ראובן נקרא ולא
מתרגם. Maaseh Reuven nikra v'lo metargem. The story of ראובן Reuven sleeping
with, you know, with בלהה, Bilhah, is read and but not translated.
Because we don't want, well, we'll see why, but you know, it's
a shameful thing and we're concerned for ראובן's Reuven's honor.
מעשה תמר נקרא ומתרגם. Maaseh Tamar nikra umetargem. The story with תמר
Tamar and יהודה Yehuda is read and translated, because even though it
starts off bad, יהודה Yehuda owns up and so on.
מעשה עגל הראשון נקרא ומתרגם. Maaseh Eigel HaRishon nikra umetargem. The story
of the first עגל, Eigel, you see you didn't realize there were
two עגלים, eigels, should be the first story of the עגל Eigel
is read and translated. והשני נקרא ולא מתרגם, V'hasheini nikra v'lo metargem,
read and not translated. What's the first, what's the second? We'll talk
about that. ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim,
the ברכה brocha of the כהנים, Kohanim, מעשה דוד ואמנון, Maaseh Dovid
v'Amnon, and now if you're into the הפטרות, Haftorahs, the story of
דוד Dovid and אמנון, Amnon, right? And how אמנון Amnon with, you
know, תמר, Tamar, the sister, and the rape and all of that.
Yeah, it's not our הפטרה, Haftorah, but apparently maybe sometimes they would
read it. Again, they didn't have everything totally fixed. נקראים ולא מתרגמים
Nikra'im v'lo mitargemim are read and not translated. Again, that's by the
way interesting, the way it joins those two together, one from the
תורה Torah and one from the נביאים. Nevi'im. Until now each one
had been dealt with individually, and it's the same הלכה, halacha, read
and not translated. Okay, so those are very curious. דוד Dovid and
אמנון Amnon you can imagine why, ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim is harder
to understand.
Is it דוד Dovid and בת שבע Bas-Sheva and אמנון? Amnon?
So also not
excluded.
Okay, it says אמנון Amnon and תמר. Tamar.
It is אמנון Amnon and תמר. Tamar. Okay. אין
מפטירין במעשה מרכבה. Ein maftirin be'maaseh Merkava. You do not have a
הפטרה Haftorah in מעשה מרכבה, Maaseh Merkava, the beginning of יחזקאל, Yechezkel,
right? Because it's type of divine mysteries. רבי יהודה מתיר, Rabbi Yehuda
matir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows it. Presumably regardless of whether you're
going to be מתרגם metargem or not, you just don't read it
at all. Maybe it's too dangerous, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda isn't
bothered. You look at תוספות Tosafot says קיימא לן כרבי יהודה Kayma
lan k'Rabbi Yehuda as we know when we do on שבועות Shavuos
morning. My explanation usually is that if you stayed up all night
learning, everybody's asleep for the הפטרה Haftorah anyway so it doesn't matter.
רבי אליעזר אומר אין מפטירין בהודעת ירושלים. Rabbi Eliezer omer ein maftirin
b'hoda'at Yerushalayim. You don't have the הפטרה Haftorah of
informed Jerusalem of all of its sins. That's inappropriate to read about
a הפטרה. Haftorah. Again, there are ברכות brochos and קללות klalos in
the תורה, Torah, you know, but we don't take a הפטרה Haftorah
that is so much about a bad. Now of course you could
say, well what do you mean, I mean there's stuff like leading
up to תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and so on. But as we'll
see in the גמרא, Gemara, it more has to do with the
fact that by, like, you're setting up yourself, the reader of the
הפטרה, Haftorah, as the one that I'm going to tell you what
your sins are. Somehow it has to do with the phrasing as
well, not just a more sort of, you know, the words of
the נביא Navi to the Jewish people. Okay, again the fact that
it has to tell you things you're not allowed to do the
הפטרה Haftorah reflects a reality that there was more choice available, these
things were not exactly fixed. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. יש
נקראין ומתרגמין ויש נקראין ולא מתרגמין ויש לא נקראין ולא מתרגמין. Yesh
nikrain umitargemin v'yesh nikrain v'lo mitargemin v'yesh lo nikrain v'lo mitargemin. Some
things you read and do תרגום, Targum, almost everything. Some things you
read, you'll be prepared to read but not to provide the תרגום
Targum for. And some things you won't even read.
אלו נקראין ומתרגמין. Elu nikrain umitargemin. The following are read and translated.
I mean of course the standard is everything, but the following are
things you might have imagined are problematic, and nevertheless we're going to
say you do the reading with the תרגום. Targum. By the way,
this idea that you might read it but not do the תרגום
Targum because it's okay for some people to hear it but you
don't necessarily want the wide audience here that they might somehow, you
know, might be embarrassing or they might misunderstand. You know, it sort
of like reflects what you find sometimes today in these like English
הלכה halacha handbooks where you have certain things in English and then
you have like in the
footnote some more leniencies and other discussion that you don't want to
present in English. It doesn't work when you're trying to publish one
in Israel and everybody understands the Hebrew in the footnote. Okay, but
the idea what things are in translation and what things are not
in translation. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so the following
you read and translate even though you might have imagined they would
be problematic. מעשה בראשית. Maaseh Bereishis.
So the בל"ט Beis Lamed Tes אכ"ן Aleph Kaf Nun ולאכננש"פ, V'Lamed
Aleph Kaf Nun Nun Shin Peh,
those are going to be the ראשי תיבות. rashei teivos. The first
one is the ב, Beis, בראשית. Bereishis. נקרא ומתרגם. Nikra umetargem. פשיטא,
Peshita, obviously,
why shouldn't you read בראשית? Bereishis? No, מהו דתימא אתו לשיולי מה
למעלה מה למטה. Ma d'teima atui l'shaylei ma l'mala ma l'mata. You're
going to come to ask about the mysteries of creation. What's above?
What's below? You know, what exists outside of the universe? מה לפנים
מה לאחור. Ma l'fnim ma l'achor. What happened... what happened before the
universe was created, what will happen afterwards? You'll ask these deep sort
of philosophical or metaphysical questions and it won't be sort of healthy
for your religious life. קא משמע לן Kama Shmelan that we're not
so concerned. I mean, you're not supposed to explore them, which we'll
learn in חגיגה, Hagigah, but the fact that you'll be a little
curious, we're not afraid it's going to go anywhere, that'll be a
problem. מעשה לוט ושתי בנותיו נקרא ומתרגם, Maaseh Lot v'shtei bnotav nikra
u-metargem, the story with Lot and his two daughters, even though there
was obviously a whole result of incest there. פשיטא pishita obviously. No,
מהו דתימא ניחוש לכבודו דאברהם. mahu de-teima neichush lichvodo d'Avram.
We're not concerned that it's embarrassing for Lot, because you know, he
wasn't Jewish. But maybe it's embarrassing for אברהם? Avram? I mean, this
whole one that he prayed for, and his relative, and got saved
on account of him, and then look what happened. קא משמע לן
Kama Shmelan that it's not—doesn't reflect badly on אברהם Avram or, you
know, maybe it's a little bit of a problem, but obviously the
importance of transmitting the story outweighs. You know, מעשה תמר—it's Maaseh Tamar
got—it's quite fascinating, of course, because you know, it's sort of like—it's
like a little bit, you know, like God—you know, if the תורה
Torah is from God, then God wanted the people to know it.
But here we are and we're to decide there's some people who
can know it and some people who can't know it. Like, you
know, sometimes when they print nowadays certain תשובות teshuvos of people and
like, the family decides they're not going to include certain of the
תשובות teshuvos because they don't think it's like, you know, it's appropriate
for everybody to sort of—to, you know, when he deals with a
sensitive issue or maybe a little too progressive for the family or
whatever it is. The question is like, yeah, but he felt it
was appropriate to write that for everybody to know. So you have
to sort of think that it's a little theologically interesting that the
Rabbis are saying, this really be in the תורה, Torah, but we
don't—it's not necessarily appropriate for everybody to know about it. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara continues: מעשה תמר ויהודה נקרא ומתרגם. Maaseh Tamar v'Yehudah
nikra u-metargem. The story יהודה Yehudah and תמר. Tamar. פשיטא pishita obvious.
And well, maybe it's not obvious, you know, it's a whole embarrassing
thing that led up to it. You know, he was looking for
a prostitute. So מהו דתימא ניחוש לכבודו דיהודה. mahu de-teima neichush lichvodo
d'Yehudah.
Maybe we should try to protect יהודה's Yehudah honor? קא משמע לן
שבחיה Kama Shmelan shvachie
actually it winds up being praiseworthy of him. דאודי d'odei that he
wound up admitting to what he had done wrong, you know. So
he sinned, fine, that's embarrassing, but the fact that he's a model
of תשובה teshuvah and admitting, that's obviously a much greater point. מעשה
עגל נקרא ומתרגם ראשון נקרא ומתרגם. Maaseh egel nikra u-metargem rishon nikra
u-metargem. The first story of the עגל egel is read and translated.
Again, well so I'll—okay, I'll tell you what the second one is.
פשיטא pishita obvious. מהו דתימא ניחוש לכבודן של ישראל. mahu de-teima neichush
lichvodan shel Yisrael. Maybe you want to protect the honor of the
Jewish people, that they did this terrible sin and we're going to
read about it? קא משמע לן Kama Shmelan it teaches us that
we're not concerned. Why not? Because in fact, כל שכן דניחא להו
דהוי להו כפרה. kol she-kein denicha lehu d'havei lehu kaparah. It's good
that people should be embarrassed, because their embarrassment is a little bit
of a כפרה. kaparah. Like the idea that they suffer—again, they're not
alive exactly right now to suffer, but you know, we representing them
are suffering. That serves as something of a כפרה. kaparah. Interesting, if
you say that, you could say that by all the other stuff
as well, but obviously this is a very weighty sin. We just
had תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, you know, which was—that was with the
מרגלים, meraglim, but you have these weighty sins that lead—like are go
through the generations and maybe this one needs like some type of
additional כפרה. kaparah. Again, it's fascinating, it's not like, well, maybe there's
other lessons to learn from it even though—but I guess, you know,
maybe that's whatever. Even though it is embarrassing for them, I mean,
how are we supposed to actually—what you want—you want to learn the
whole story of—of, you know, of שמות Shemos and the Exodus or
whatever and not have עגל egel as a part of that story?
But anyway, so it's a—exactly, it's a little funny exactly sort of
what the גמרא Gemara considers what the הוה אמינא'ס hava aminas were
and what the trade-offs are. Now, what's the first עגל egel as
opposed to the second? You know what, let me get—we'll get to
the second one and then I'll discuss what it means by the
first one and the second. Let's keep on reading. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this...
okay.
קללות וברכות נקראין ומתרגמין. Klalos u-brachos nikra u-metargemim. The קללות klalos and
the ברכות, brachos, you know, are read and translated. So the גמרא
Gemara says: פשיטא. pishita. Yeah, בחקותי Bechukosai presumably.
And פשיטא pishita or, you know, כי תשא. Ki Sisa. So the
גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא pishita obviously, מהו דתימא ניחוש דחלשא דעתייהו דציבורא.
mahu de-teima neichush d'chalsha da'atayhu de-tzibbura.
Maybe the sort of the, you know, the spirit of the—of the
community will be—despaired or—how does it translate חלשא דעתייהו? chalsha da'atayhu? Would
be, um, not despaired exactly, but... despondent? What does it
say? Paga? No, like
לפוג, lafog, yeah, disheartened. Okay, maybe they'll be disheartened like, oh my
god, all this terrible stuff is going to happen to us. So
קא משמע לן Kama Shmelan that we're not concerned about that. Why—why
aren't we concerned about that again? Maybe it's good, it'll keep you
to doing the right things, you won't keep you
to do the מצוות—the mitzvos עבירות. aveiros. Okay. רש"י Rashi
we had a different גירסא, girsa, which is maybe we're afraid people
will do it from אהבה ויראה, ahavah v'yirah, they'll do it exactly
they'll be out of fear of the reward and punishment.
אזהרות ועונשין נקראין ומתרגמין. Azharos v'onshin nikra u-metargemim. The warnings and the
punishments. I mean, that's like half of the תורה. Torah. But the
punishments that you get for doing wrong things, you're going to translate
that. פשיטא pishita obviously. No, מהו דתימא ניחוש דאתו למעבד מיראה, mahu
de-teima neichush d'atu l'me'evad mi-yirah, maybe they'll only going to do it
because they're afraid they'll be punished. So maybe you should just read
the מצוות? mitzvos? Funny, we're going to edit God's תורה, Torah, right?
So much of the תורה Torah is... do this or you'll get
punished, right, especially, especially in דברים, Devarim, but we're going to sort
of try to not translate that, so massage the message a little
bit. קמשמע לן ka mashma lan that we're not going to do
that. Again, I just see the theological הוה אמינא'ס hava amina's here
as fascinating, and they're not only הוה אמינא'ס hava amina's because when
we get to things we're not מתרגם, metargem, we actually are making
certain choices.
מעשה אמנון ותמר נקרא ומתרגם. Ma'aseh Amnon ve-Tamar nikra u-mitargem. The story
of Amnon and Tamar. Now, the גמרא Gemara will discuss that. So
you translate. מעשה אבשלום, Ma'aseh Avshalom, again all these stories in דוד'ס
David's families, נקרא ומתרגם. nikra u-mitargem. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. מהו דתימא ליחוש
ליקריה דדוד, Mah de-teima leichush likraya de-David, let's be concerned of David's
honor, that although you know, bad things in the family doesn't reflect
good on the father, קמשמע לן ka mashma lan that now it
doesn't tell you קמשמע לן ka mashma lan why that way, but
again presumably because it's not directly about דוד. David. מעשה פילגש בגבעה,
Ma'aseh pilegesh be-Giva, the story about פילגש בגבעה, pilegesh be-Giva, נקרא ומתרגם,
nikra u-mitargem, you translate. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. No, מהו דתימא ליחוש לכבודא
דבנימין, Mah de-teima leichush lichvoda de-Binyamin, the honor of שבט בנימין, shevet
Binyamin, קמשמע לן ka mashma lan that it's really reflects more on
the particular individuals, not on the whole שבט. shevet. You know, again,
in a way this seems again I say like a little funny,
but you know you have had you have this even in contemporary
scholarly debate, you know when like Steinsaltz wrote his book on biblical
figures, what was it called, Biblical Figures, you know, he got put
in חרם cherem by רב שך Rav Shach because he described them
as human beings, you know, and he didn't describe them and he
described them closer to the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim and
not in the more angelic terms, you know, perfect terms that you
find in certain מדרשים. midrashim. How much do people learn better from
hearing about people's failings and how much is that sort of the
message of the תורה Torah and how much have we tried to
cover it all up and make them feel like seem like perfect?
Is that better for like pedagogical and you know and more and
moral education? So that maybe something here, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't
speak so much from the pedagogy perspective as much as just protecting
people's honor. הודע
את ירושלים את תועבותיה, Hoda et Yerushalayim et to'avoteha, that is the
what we had in our משנה. mishnah. נקרא ומתרגם Nikra u-mitargem is
read and translated. פשיטא, Pshita, obvious. I mean, you know, it's one
of those many
נביאים nevi'im that are castigating the Jewish people. No, לאפוקי מדרבי אליעזר,
le-apuki mi-de-Rabbi Eliezer, to exclude the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
דתניא, De-tanya, and now we'll get we'll see what the issue was
with this. מעשה באדם אחד שהיה קורא למעלה מרבי אליעזר, Ma'aseh be-adam
echad she-haya korei le-ma'ala me-Rabbi Eliezer, a person was reading above רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. It's interesting, יורד לפני התיבה yored lifnei ha-teiva and
here he's reading above, right, so question about being on type of
some בימה bimah when you're reading the תורה, Torah, it seems to
be. הודע את ירושלים את תועבותיה. Hoda et Yerushalayim et to'avoteha. אמר
לו, Amar lo, he said to him, עד שאתה בודק בתועבות ירושלים,
ad she-ata bodek be-to'avot Yerushalayim, by saying let Jerusalem know its sins,
like you're positioning yourself as if, you know, although you're reading the
נביא, navi, but like as if speaking in God's in God's name,
and you're the one being the address, so you're here to be
to inspect Jerusalem and to, you know, to inform them of their
sins. You're putting yourself over the people and saying I'm going to
let you know all of your sins. So while you're busy checking
out the sins of Jerusalem, צא ובדוק בתועבות אמך, tzei u-vdok be-to'avot
imecha, go go check out your mother's sins, like very fascinating response.
בדקו אחריו ומצאו בו שמץ פסול. Badku acharay u-matzu bo shemetz pasul.
They searched after him and they found that actually he had some
questionable genealogy. So did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer know that and he
was making that point? Did he just say it as a type
of a as a retort and it wound up that of you
know that it wound up being true even though he wasn't aware
of it? But the basic point is who are you to put
yourself? People in glass houses shouldn't throw stones. Who are you to
put yourself in a position where you're sort of, again, I think
it's the particular language. We read a lot of נביאים nevi'im that
say לכו נא ונוכחה, lechu na ve-nivachacha, you know, let's come and
you know speak about the people's sins, but it's הודע, hoda, like
you're the one that's going to be standing over Jerusalem and telling
it sins.
Isn't it מעשה העגל Ma'aseh ha-Egel there?
I mean why isn't it מעשה העגל? Ma'aseh ha-Egel?
No, meaning we think we don't do it.
Yeah, that was his opinion. He got upset at about it. Anyway,
whatever he was anyway. So okay, ואלו נקרין ולא מתרגמין, Ve-elu nikrin
ve-lo mitargemin, the following are read and not translated. רב דן Rav
Dan is the ראשי תיבות. rashei teivot.
Was the עגל, Egel, was that a voluntary choice of a הפטרה?
haftarah?
It seems to be, right, that's the whole fact that you have
to say certain things you do as הפטרות haftarot and certain things
you don't,
right. So seems that like I was saying before that it's not
fixed what the הפטרה haftarah was, right? Maybe there were different different
traditions in different communities. Maybe it was all there was a lot
of like latitude, you know, it's not exactly clear the degree of
flux that was in play. Now of course it's interesting, right, because
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying you don't even read it and we
go to the opposite extreme, you read it and you translate it.
ואלו נקרין ולא מתרגמין, Ve-elu nikrin ve-lo mitargemin, we're going to get
to the עגל. Egel. You read the following but you don't translate.
מעשה ראובן נקרא ולא מתרגם.
Ma'aseh
Reuven nikra ve-lo mitargem.
מעשה ברבי חנינא בן גמליאל, Ma'aseh be-Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel, excuse me,
שהלך לכבול she-halach le-Chavul והיה קורא חזן הכנסת ve-haya korei chazan ha-knesset
and the חזן chazan was reading. Interesting that it assigns this to
the חזן, chazan, right, because the חזן chazan is often the person
who's more like the גבאי. gabbai. Anyway here it has him as
the reader. ויהי בשכון ישראל בארץ ההיא vayehi bishkon Yisrael b'aretz hahi
וילך ראובן, vayelech Reuven, what is it? וישכב את בלהה פילגש אביו,
vayishkav et Bilhah pilegesh aviv, וישמע ישראל, vayishma Yisrael, ויהיו בני ישראל,
vayihyu bnei Yisrael, same, ויהיו בני יעקב, vayihyu bnei Yaakov, בני יעקב
שנים עשר. bnei Yaakov shneim asar. So it says ואמר לו למתורגמן,
v'amar lo l'meturgeman, so Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel said to the מתורגמן,
meturgeman, not to the reader, you're allowed to read it. He said
to him, right, yeah, you do read it. He said either הפסק,
hafsek, stop, or the question is if that word is in there.
אל תתרגמהו אלא אחרון. al t'targmehu ela acharon. Only read the second,
only read the second half of the verse. Just say ויהיו
בני יעקב שנים עשר. vayehiyu bnei Yaakov shneim asar. Don't write וילך
ראובן וישכב את בלהה פילגש אביו. vayelech Reuven vayishkav et Bilhah pilegesh
aviv. ושבחוהו חכמים, v'shibchuhu chachamim, and the חכמים chachamim praised Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel. Oh, that was great that you stopped the מתורגמן. meturgeman.
Again, indicating that there might have been some, this wasn't widespread, these
practices of not doing the תרגום tirgum or they hadn't yet been
established yet, or again points I've made, which is it's the rabbis
visiting שולס, shuls, the rabbis weren't the authorities in the שולס, shuls,
so maybe they're trying to have their positions having some influence in
the שולס. shuls. Who were the חכמים? chachamim? Were the חכמים chachamim
like the local sages there? And here was a visiting rabbi who
more came from this tradition. Anyway, מעשה עגל השני נקרא ולא מתרגם.
maaseh eigel hashani nikra v'lo mitargem. So now we're going to get
to the second story of the עגל, eigel, which is not translated.
What do you mean the first and the second? So איזו מעשה
עגל השני? eizo maaseh eigel hashani? What's the story of the second
עגל? eigel? Mean ויאמר משה עד וירא משה. vayomer Moshe ad vayar
Moshe. So, so from ויאמר משה vayomer Moshe until וירא משה. vayar
Moshe. So what is this exactly? So רש״י Rashi says it means
that you don't read the part where משה Moshe says to אהרן
Aharon or אהרן Aharon says, you know, that, that what you read
the part where משה Moshe says where the תורה Torah says about,
you know, what happened when it's describing the events, but the second
story is the retelling of the events when משה Moshe says to
אהרן, Aharon, what did this people do to you? And he says,
you know, about what is it? ואשליכהו באש ויצא העגל הזה. va'ashlichehu
ba'esh vayetzei haeigel hazeh. But you don't want to read
that because ואשליכהו, va'ashlichehu, what is it?
ואשליכהו באש ויצא העגל הזה. va'ashlichehu ba'esh vayetzei haeigel hazeh. But you
don't want to read that because ויצא העגל הזה vayetzei haeigel hazeh
makes it sound like there was some power to it, that it
actually came out on its own, that so maybe it suggests there
was some actual power, you know, independent type of divine power to
the עגל. eigel. תוספות Tosafot has a different story, a different version.
If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says, מעשה עגל השני נקרא
ולא מתרגם, maaseh eigel hashani nikra v'lo mitargem, פירש רש״י שלא יאמרו
ממשות היה בו, peirash Rashi shelo yomru mamashut haya bo, מדאמר אהרן
ויצא העגל הזה. mid'amar Aharon vayetzei haeigel hazeh. וקשיא דירושלמי, v'kashya d'Yerushalmi,
ובירושלמי איתא הכי, u'v'Yerushalmi ita hachi, and it says like this, he
says, לכן נראה לפרש בירושלמי, lachen nira l'fareish b'Yerushalmi, it's four lines
from the end of תוספות, Tosafot, starting four lines from the word
ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, דטעמא הוי דאין דומה גנותו של יחיד ביחיד d'taama havei
d'ein domeh gnuto shel yachid b'yachid או של ציבור בציבור o shel
tzibur b'tzibur לגנותו של יחיד בציבור. l'gnuto shel yachid b'tzibur. Fascinating, right?
If an individual is embarrassed in private, it's one thing. Or if
the whole community is embarrassed in front of the whole community, it's
also one thing. It's alright. But the worst thing is you're an
individual and your shame is being exposed in the larger community. משום
כבודו של אהרן לא רצה לתרגם. mishum kvodo shel Aharon lo ratza
l'targem. It's when משה Moshe berates אהרן, Aharon, right? It says,
ולשמצה בקמיהם, u'l'shimtza b'kameihem, that what you have done to them, that's
going to cause, they're going to, it's going to be an embarrassment
for them for, you know, in, in future generations. So according to
them what's cut out is not the problem of אהרן Aharon saying
ויצא העגל הזה, vayetzei haeigel hazeh, it's משה Moshe saying מה עשה
לך העם הזה כי הבאת עליו חטאה גדולה, mah asa lecha ha'am
hazeh ki hiveita alav chata'ah gdolah, like when משה Moshe is castigating
him in a sense of like a public castigation, and he is
being sort of the individual in front of like in the larger
context of the whole ציבור. tzibur. Although that is the sort of
embarrassment that we're trying to preserve אהרן Aharon from.
Yeah. But first of all, מעשה אמנון ותמר נקרא ומתרגם, maaseh Amnon
v'Tamar nikra u'mitargem, which is יחיד yachid never mentioned in a ציבור,
tzibur, but we're still doing that.
Well, but that wasn't דוד. David. That wasn't people whose honors we
were so focused on protecting.
Okay, but then the other thing is why don't they gloss over,
you know, מכירת יוסף, mechirat Yosef, which is...
Yeah, a lot of good stories, like which other ones we're trying
to protect. I mean, the תורה Torah has a lot of troubling
stories in it, which is just part of the power of the
תורה. Torah. So I don't know the answer to that. Let's go
back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay.
So תניא, tanya, we turn on a ברייתא. braita. רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, לעולם יהא אדם זהיר בתשובתו.
l'olam yehei adam zahir b'tshuvato. A person should always be careful in
how you respond, maybe particularly when you're being attacked, you know, or,
or questioned, exactly how you're going to respond. שמתוך תשובה שהשיב אהרן
למשה, shemitoch tshuva sheheshiv Aharon l'Moshe, because of the, in the way
that אהרן Aharon responded to משה, Moshe, פרקו המעוררים. porku hame'orerim. That's
gave a license for those that were sort of the skeptics, the
questioners to, to, you know, to cast off from themselves the divine
yoke, you know, to, to be heretical. שנאמר ואשליכהו באש ויצא העגל
הזה. shene'emar va'ashlichehu ba'esh vayetzei haeigel hazeh. Sounds like the עגל eigel
came out all by itself. Which is why רש״י Rashi says reasonably
that that's why we're not מתרגם mitargem is because of that פסוק.
pasuk. Okay. ברכת כהנים נקרא ולא מתרגם. birkat kohanim nikra v'lo mitargem.
This has got to be the most bizarre one. ברכת כהנים birkat
kohanim which they would do on a daily basis in the בית
כנסת, beit knesset, you would not do the תרגום. tirgum. What's the
matter with the תרגום? tirgum? It's a wonderful ברכה. bracha. מאי טעמא?
mai taama? משום דכתיב ישא. mishum dichitv yissa. ישא ה׳ פניו אליך.
yissa Hashem panav eilecha. And the whole idea of נשיאת פנים, nesiat
panim, right? What's a judge? A judge is אשר לא ישא פנים
ולא יקח שוחד asher lo yissa panim v'lo yikach shochad is God,
right? לא תשא, lo tissa, right? The whole prohibition about giving... showing
special favor. So here we say that God shows special favor to
Israel, it seems that God is not playing fair, not being objective,
and that’s something
that people could find problematic. Of course, generally Jews didn't usually until
like the modern era have a problem with sort of עם סגולה,
Am Segulah, the particularism and the special favor whatever. But nevertheless, it
would raise certain questions, especially if the Torah says that you're not
supposed to be נושא פנים. nose panim. Okay.
Or maybe is it just as simple as outside people?
Maybe because it's translated, there'll be people that are not so פרום
frum or not so... maybe more marginal people. That's an interesting question,
which maybe gets to the issue I was raising in terms of
second-guessing God in terms of what are you translating? That maybe the
more seriously committed ones knew the Hebrew and this was talking about
the more marginal ones. I have no idea if that's historically accurate
or not. I'm absolutely...
It must be marginal
but just it's in their face. I understand, I understand. It's a
really interesting question. Like, who knew? Who was able to understand biblical
Hebrew and who was really not? Now clearly part of the answer
is Hellenized Jews, right? The Hellenized Jews, but of course did they
understand Aramaic or did they understand Greek? So I don't know which
is the class of people that understood Aramaic and didn't understand the
biblical Hebrew. That would be like a real interesting thing to research.
Okay. מעשה דוד ואמנון לא נקרין ולא מתרגמין: Ma'aseh David ve'Amnon lo
nikrin velo metargamin: the story of David and Amnon you don't read
it. והא אמרת מעשה אמנון ותמר נקרין ומתרגמין: ve'ha amarta ma'aseh Amnon
ve'Tamar nikrin u'metargamin: but you just said the story of Amnon and
Tamar you read and you translate? It's the same story! לא קשיא
הא דכתיב אמנון בן דוד הא דכתיב אמנון סתמא: Lo kashya, ha
de'chtiv Amnon Ben David, ha de'chtiv Amnon stama: you don't read the
verses that identify him as David's son, אמנון בן דוד, Amnon Ben
David, you want to protect David's honor, and you even skip over
those verses because not only you don't translate them, you don't read
them. But the ones that just speak about אמנון, Amnon, so it's
vaguely, we know, exactly, it's less of an issue of David's honor.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כל המקראות הכתובים בתורה לגנאי קורא אותן לשבח.
Kol ha-mikra'ot ha-ktuvim ba-Torah l'gnai, koreh otan l'shavach. Now this is an
again a fascinating idea of changing, not literally changing but changing at
least the way people hear it and it's read, the biblical text.
Biblical verses that are written לגנאי, l'gnai, now this doesn't mean like
insulting, but it means almost like the language is offensive. It doesn't
just mean it says bad things or terrible things the Torah says
in the קללות, klallot, but actually offensive language, you read it in
more euphemistic terms. Quite fascinating when you realize that just yesterday, on
yesterday's דף daf was the whole point about not giving a euphemistic
translation of certain verses that is against the הלכה. halacha. But this
isn't הלכה halacha and this is more-less the same word except it's
slightly toned down. So let's take a look.
לשבח. l'shavach. כגון ישגלנה, k'gon yishgalena, which means to sleep with...
ישגלנה, yishgalena, excuse me, which means to sleep, but it's a very
crass way of saying to sleep. And you read ישכבנה, yishkavena, to
lie with, as opposed to other verbs that might say the same
thing in a much crasser way. בעפולים, ba-apolim, God should smite you
בעפולים, ba-apolim, which is a type of,
what do you call...? what it is? Hemorrhoids, thank you. Okay. So
but it refers to obviously the anus and so on in a
very crass way. And you write בטחורים, ba-tchorim, which refers to it
in a slightly more delicate way. And that's what we do actually
when we read those פסוקים. psukim. Okay. So those are the two
that are in the Torah. Here are some that are not in
the Torah.
חריונים: chiryonim: so חריונים chiryonim which means sort of also their excrement,
but in a sort of crass way. And you read דביונים, dovyonim,
like their flow, of birds and whatever they're talking about, bird excrement.
לאכול את חריהם: le'echol et chareihem: we're worried about the crass word.
Michael, there are curse words like this, okay? We're worried about the
crassness of the word, not about the bad thing it's describing. Okay,
right. So לאכול את חריהם, le'echol et chareihem, excrement. ולשתות את מימי
שיניהם: ve'lishtot et meimei shineihem: to drink the... funny word, water of
their teeth. Teeth here means Rashi says it means sort of like
their intestines, although, maybe... so we read לאכול את צואתם, le'echol et
tzo'atam, that would be like excrement. It wouldn't be such crass words.
ולשתות את מימי רגליהם: ve'lishtot et meimei ragleihem: like their leg water,
which is again clearly a euphemism, but as opposed to yesterday's euphemisms,
it's a euphemism that it's clear what it means. It's just a
more delicate term. למחראות: lamachra'ot: again the word למחראות lamachra'ot is again
like excrement, what?
Is it that מימי שיניהם meimei shineihem means loose stools?
Loose stools, right. I said intestines. Right. But that's funny because מי
רגליים mei raglayim usually means urine, so actually it is funny that
translation.
Which is supported by the three teeth-like glands.
Okay fine. למחראות: lamachra'ot: again a word of excrement. למוצאות: lemotza'ot: the
things that they excrete.
So again, that refers back to the word excrement, מוצא, motza, to
excrete. Okay. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha Omer:
למחראות כשמן. lamachra'ot kishman. No, that you actually read it the way
it is. מפני שגנאי לעבודת כוכבים mipnei she'gnai le'avodat kochavim because it's
referring to idols and therefore you can say curse words in regards
to idolatry. You can say those bad words. אמר רב נחמן: Amar
Rav Nachman: said Rav Nachman, כל ליצנותא אסורה: kol leitzanuta assura: any
type of mocking
is
forbidden, בר מליצנותא. bar mi-leitzanuta. is a very powerful way of undermining
it.
דשריא, Deshareya, permissible, דכתיב, dechtiv, כרע בל קרס נבו, Kara Bel Karas
Nevo, Bel bows down,
Nevo splashes, how do they translate this? I'm sorry. Nevo squats, Nevo
splashes. Okay, bows down and splashes. דכתיב, dechtiv, קרסו כרעו יחדיו, Karsu
karau yachdav, they have bowed down and they have fallen together, לא
יכלו מלט משא, lo yachlu maleit massa, they could not escape the
burden.
Or they say they cannot deliver the burden.
Okay, cannot deliver the burden, which means like what, they can't excrete?
Oh, I see. Okay, that makes sense. Okay. So basically it's saying
look, you know, it's mocking them. It's like saying, oh, you know,
they can't even go to the bathroom, these idols. All right. רבי
ינאי אומר מהכא, Rabbi Yannai omer meihacha, לעגלות בית און יגורו שכן
שמרון, Le'aglot Beit Aven yaguru shechein Shomron, for the calves of Beit
Aven will fear the dwellers of Shomron, כי אבל עליו עמו, ki
avel alav amo, because the nation is mourning over it, וכמריו עליו
יגילו, uchmarav alav yagilu, and its priests will rejoice על כבודו, al
kvodo, on its honor, כי גלה ממנו. ki gala mimenu. Wait, no,
יגילו yagilu doesn't mean rejoice, I mean it does mean rejoice, but
it doesn't make sense in this context. How do they translate that?
It means people mourn over it and likewise its priests who had
rejoiced.
Oh, who had rejoiced. Okay. And the priests who had rejoiced will
mourn על כבודו כי גלה, al kvodo ki gala, for its honor
that it has been exiled ממנו. mimenu. אל תקרי כבודו, Al tikrei
kvodo, do not read its honor, אלא כבידו, ela kveido,
its weight, which maybe again here means like its excrement or something.
Okay, so anyway, again just a proof that you're allowed to make
fun because it's only being made fun of in the verse, but
the way he's reading the verse. Anyway,
אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Amar
Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmei deRav Acha brei deRav Ika, שרי ליה
לבר ישראל למימר ליה לעבודת כוכבים, sharei lei levar Yisrael lemeimar lei
la'avodat kochavim, it's permitted for a
Jew to say to an idolator, שקלי לעבודת כוכבים, shakli la'avodat kochavim,
take your idol, ואנחי בשין תיו, veanchei beshin tav, and stick it
up your shin-tav. Okay, I think you can figure out what that
means. Okay. שילו. shilo. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, האי מאן
דסני
שמעניה, hai man desanei shamanei, somebody who has a bad reputation, שרי
ליה לבזויי
בגימל שין, sharei lei levazuyei begimel shin, you can sort of insult
him, embarrass him with gimel-shin. Or what exactly gimel-shin is not clear.
רש"י Rashi says it means maybe saying like his mother was a
prostitute or something. Again, this issue about talking about people's mothers.
So האי מאן דשפיר שמעניה, hai man deshafir shamanei, and somebody who
has a good reputation, which is a little bit funny because just
because somebody has a bad reputation doesn't mean he actually did something
bad, you know, unless it means that he has earned the bad
reputation. But again, why we're bringing in the mother is not clear.
A somebody who has a good reputation, שרי ליה לשבוחיה, sharei lei
leshabuchei, you're allowed to praise him. Well, that's not a חידוש. chidush.
ומן דשבכיה, Uman deshavchei, and even the one who praises him, ינוחו
לו ברכות על ראשו, yanuchu lo brachot al rosho, even the person
who praises him should be blessed. So again, further filling in this
idea here of our responsibility in terms of how we, you know,
I think it echoes this whole idea of נקרא ומתרגם, nikra umitargem,
that you can't just say oh, you know, facts are facts and
so on, it's our responsibility. Do we tell things over, not tell
things over? What type of a frame do we put it in?
What type of a way do we, you know, sort of position
them, talk about them, and so on? So here sort of translating
in from the verses to our interaction with other people raises interesting
questions: לשון הרע, lashon hara, public embarrassment, and so on, which the
גמרא Gemara is not exploring. הדרן עלך הקורא את המגילה עומד. Hadran
alach Hakoreh et ha-Megilla Omed. So that is the end of that
פרק, perek, which got started us with ways to read the מגילה
Megilla but really focused a lot on reading of the תורה, Torah,
reading of the הפטרה, haftarah, תרגום, targum, and other types of things
that were done in שול. shul. Now we get to the last
פרק, perek, which gets us to actually the בית הכנסת Beit ha-Knesset
itself, a very, a very interesting פרק perek about the whole nature
of קדושת בית הכנסת. Kiddushat Beit ha-Knesset. Again, fascinating that the רי"ף
Rif and the רמב"ם Rambam and other ראשונים, Rishonim, a number of
them had the fourth פרק perek as the third, and I don't
understand at all what the sort of flow would be from talking
about the way you read the מגילה Megilla to the קדושה kedusha
of the בית הכנסת Beit ha-Knesset and then going back to the
way you read the מגילה. Megilla. So this order makes a lot
more sense, although we should again note that some many ראשונים Rishonim
had this פרק perek as the third פרק. perek. Let's take a
look. בני עיר שמכרו רחובה של עיר, Benei ir shemachru rechovah shel
ir, if the people of the city sold the city square, and
as we remember from תענית, Taanit, they would go into the city
square to do these public prayers on the fast days, so רחובה,
rechovah, usually presumably it would be used for other types of, you
know, non-religious purposes, but every now and then you'd use it for
a public religious gathering. So the assumption here is that it has
a certain level of קדושה. kedusha. So in that case, לוקחין בדמיה
בית הכנסת, lokchin bidmei Beit ha-Knesset, you can use the money to
go up in קדושה, kedusha, you can buy a synagogue, which obviously
is a place that's dedicated for תפילה. tefilla. בית הכנסת, Beit ha-Knesset,
if you sold a בית הכנסת, לוקחין תיבה, Beis Hakneset lokchim teiva,
you can go ahead and buy the בימה, bimah, you know, where
you're going to put the תורה Torah down on, which is a
higher level of קדושה. kedusha. So there's a big question here. What
do you do with the place itself? If you sell the שוק,
shuk, can you use the שוק shuk for any purpose? This is
just saying what do you do with the money, right? So that's
going to be a whole other question. question about what do you
do with the actual שול shul *shul* that you sold, what types
and the person who buys it, you know, what types of things
can they use it from? I mean, there's all these fascinating הלכה
*halachic* questions like you go into like you know a lot of
places, a lot of שולס shuls, *shuls*, you could see oh this
used to be a movie theater or this used to be a
church, right? That's the other question, can you use a church? It's
really momentary. So yeah, but is it appropriate? And so when if
something used to be and when the place actually has to leave
the שול shul, *shul* because it's falling down, the neighborhood has changed,
whatever the issue is, the Jews have moved elsewhere, right? Who can
you sell it to? Right? And can you sell it to be
knocked down and something else be rebuilt? Can you sell it to
a church? What are you, you know, if they want to use
it, often it's usable for, you know, it's the same type of
thing, house of worship, you know, it makes you know usable by
somebody of a different faith. So these are very important questions. So
that's going to be a, right, they might have the same rules?
Exactly. So anyway, that's going to be a second, a later discussion:
what can you use it for? Although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* definitely
will get introduced that earlier on as well. But the focus here
is not what can you use it for, but what can you
do with the funds? And the funds can only be reused for
something of a higher purpose. Now I want to say the end
of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* will say they can't be used for
a lower purpose, which leaves of course the obvious question about the
same purpose. Sell one שול shul *shul* to buy another שול shul,
*shul*, sell one thing to buy another thing, which fascinatingly is not
discussed in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, not even directly addressed in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, but let's take a look at that.
רחוב העיר *Rechov hair*, what does it mean to sell the public
square?
You mean who would own it? Yeah, it's I mean there I
mean, you know, you have in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* particularly if
we're thinking about like towns and villages and not cities, because let's
remember also that עיר *ir* is a town, not a city. A
city is like a כרך *kerach*. That you would have like even
private ownerships of towns, like one person like you might rent out
the whole thing. I mean, you certainly have that in feudal society,
right? That somebody like, you know, so that you actually would have
so I'm I do wonder maybe it means I don't know some
developer wants to go ahead and build something in the square.
בני העיר *Bnei hair*, they're selling it.
Oh. No, but but I'm saying but it's possible to think of
a of a priva- that's true, meaning you could the- you could
have private ownership of a whole town, but you could also have
like I assume your question was like what would it be used
what would well okay anyway. An individual could buy let me then
take a step back and somebody could buy the public square right
and want to put up a house there, right? Want to develop
it. So what exactly was the question?
I was just trying to understand what is the public square and
it feels like it's privatization.
Right, I think that's true.
I think that is what the standard usage would be. I mean,
you have you've been in places where they have these public squares
like these palazzos, right? And whatever, you know, no? You know what
I'm talking about like in Italy or whatever they have these like
that they're made דווקא *davka* for I mean it's not a park,
it's like a square for as a place for people to gather,
right?
I'm not familiar with cases where the public square is sold for
private use. Uh-huh. I'm more familiar with cases where the public square
is a requirement of private development. Uh-huh. On some level, but whatever.
Okay.
Yes, it does seem like it's privatization.
But they could have a lot more money from selling a שול
shul. *shul* than just to buy a תיבה teivah *teiva*. So what
do you do with the...
Okay, so that's going we're going to get to that in a
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*.
You haven't seen the new... Okay.
So בית הכנסת Beit ha-Knesset, לוקחים תיבה teivah, *Beis haknesses lokchim teiva*.
תיבה teivah לוקחים מטפחות mitpachot *Teiva lokchim mitpachos*. If you sell the
בימה bimah *bimah*, you can use it to buy the things that
you wrap the ספר תורה Sefer Torah, *Sefer Torah* in, so because
that's a higher קדושה kedusha *kedusha* because it's more connected to the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah, *Sefer Torah*. מטפחות יקחו ספרים *Mitpachos yikchu sefarim*.
You can actually buy now the ספרים *sefarim* here says this way
means the other ספרי תנ״ך *Sifrei Tanach* or נ״ך *Nach* but not
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah *Sefer Torah* itself. But that's כתבי קודש
*kisvei kodesh*? No. ספרים לוקחים תורה Torah, *Sefarim lokchim Torah*. And if
you sell the ספרי נ״ך *Sifrei Nach*, you can use it to
buy a ספר תורה Sefer Torah *Sefer Torah*. So that's the hierarchy.
Now I should say, where does the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* derive from?
The קדושת בית הכנסת kedushat Beit HaKnesset. *kedushat beis haknesses* at all
is a very important discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*. From our
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, a not unreasonable read would be that the קדושה
kedusha *kedusha* all derives from the ספר תורה Sefer Torah. *Sefer Torah*.
That everything here has a degree of קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* because of
its connection to the ספר תורה Sefer Torah. *Sefer Torah*. Right, so
the things you wrap the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah* in, the
things you put the ספר תורה Torah. *Sefer Torah* on, the house
that stores the בימה *bimah* with the ספר תורה Torah, *Sefer Torah*
is in and so on. Right, it's all sort of expanding circles.
And the רחוב *rechov*, you would bring the ספר תורה Torah, *Sefer
Torah* out to the רחוב *rechov*. So a in תענית Ta'anit *Taanis*.
So a very reasonable read here is that this is all a
function of the intrinsic קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* of the ספר תורה *Sefer
Torah*. But I will tell you at the outset that there are
at least two or three other interpretations of the ראשונים Rishonim. *Rishonim*.
The רמב״ן *Ramban* understands that the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* of a בית
כנסת Beit Knesset *beis knesses*, some of these things about the תיבה
*teiva* whatever is about the ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*. He understands that
the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of a בית כנסת Beit Knesset *beis knesses*
is because it's a תשמישי מצווה *tashmishei mitzvah*. He basically says it
is like a לולב lulav, *lulav*. You use a לולב lulav *lulav*
to do the מצוה *mitzvah* of shaking a לולב *lulav* and you
use a שופר *shofar* to do the מצוה *mitzvah* of blowing a
שופר *shofar* and you use a שול shul *shul* to do the
מצוה *mitzvah* of reading the Torah? דאוונינג *davening*. דאוונינג *davening* is what
he says. So for him, he says the בית כנסת *beis knesses*
is not about the ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*, it is a תשמישי
מצווה *tashmishei mitzvah* for an object as it were that you use
for תפילה tefillah *tefillah*. And that actually makes the קדושה kedusha *kedusha*
of בית כנסת *beis knesses* very minimal because what do you... you
do with a לולב after you're done using it? You throw it
out. So according to the רמב"ן, Ramban, the only question of the
קדושה kedusha, of a שול shul is who gets to decide whether
you're done using it or not. But once you're done using it,
it loses its status, very much not like this sense of intrinsic
קדושה kedusha which I think more is the more simple sense of
the discussions we're going to see. The ר"ן Ran has a different
explanation. The ר"ן Ran says it is not because of a תשמישי
מצוה tashmishe mitzvah like לולב, it is because you say in the
שול, shul he still connects it to תפילה tefillah interestingly enough תורה,
because you say in the שול shul דברים שבקדושה. devarim shebikdusha. So
since you say and we had that idea before of דברים שבקדושה
devarim shebikdusha and you need ten people and so on, like קדוש
קדוש קדוש, kadosh kadosh kadosh, the fact that it's connected to קדושה
kedusha through the דברים שבקדושה devarim shebikdusha that are said is what
gives it קדושה. kedusha. Right? Because according to the רמב"ן, Ramban, if
I just had a private house which I designated as my as
my little, you know, house where I go to דאווען ביחידות, daven
beyachidus, it would have maybe the same קדושה. kedusha, It's תשמישי מצוה.
tashmishe mitzvah. Okay, whereas according to the ר"ן, Ran, the ר"ן Ran
says no, it's because it's you use it for a מנין minyan
and you say דברים שבקדושה devarim shebikdusha gives it קדושה. kedusha, The
third explanation is that it's patterned after the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So same way we have an idea of קדושה kedusha, of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and חז"ל Chazal understand that a בית כנסת
is a מקדש מעט, Mikdash Me'at, rabbinically they gave it some type
of quasi-קדושה kedusha, to parallel that of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So one theme we're going to be looking at is קדושת בית
הכנסת. Beit Haknesset Again, I would argue in the משנה, Mishnah it's
all related to the ספר תורה, which is just expanding circles around
the ספר תורה, but you have other approach this more standard approach
is to focus it on תפילה with three ways of looking at
it: תשמישי מצוה, tashmishe mitzvah, דברים שבקדושה devarim shebikdusha and the בית
כנסת type of model, בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash type of model.
Yes.
So the big difference would be intrinsic to the ספר תורה versus
other things like תשמישי קדושה tashmishe kedusha that would be בית מדרש.
Beit Midrash.
We don't have ספר תורה in there. Right. Excellent. We're going to
get to that, although that has other sources of קדושה, the learned
תורה as opposed to the ספר תורה.
So just like a לולב then the
רמב"ן Ramban's view is that it's very difficult
you'd be able to sell it again.
Exactly. Exactly. The רמב"ן Ramban's view is a difficult view. Yes.
It's interesting you often point out how the גמרא Gemara and משנה
try to shift from the מקדש Mikdash to תורה. Right. Here where
you've actually got a there's a counterweight.
Aha! That's an interesting point.
Which was also the מקדש.
Mikdash. That's an interesting point. If you see the קדושה as sourced
in the מקדש, Mikdash, it's pointing back in the other direction as
opposed to what I was suggesting which is the קדושה here is
connected to the תורה, the ספר תורה.
Although it is connected to the תורה, I think that the גמרא
Gemara, also wants to say.
Oh,
but you mean that there's a counterweight. Oh okay. Nice.
So they don't completely abandon the other idea.
Right. Good. Okay, so אבל אם מכרו תורה לא יקחו ספרים ספרים
לא יקחו מטפחות מטפחות לא יקחו תיבה תיבה לא יקחו בית כנסת
בית כנסת לא יקחו את הרחוב וכן. aval im machru Torah lo
yikchu sefarim sefarim lo yikchu mitpachot mitpachot lo yikchu teivah teivah lo
yikchu Beit Knesset Beit Knesset lo yikchu et harechov vechen. Okay,
so that's don't go in the opposite order. Of course leaving the
big question of the most normal thing you would do if you're
selling a תיבה is buy another תיבה, right? Sell a שול, shul,
you buy another שול. shul, So it would seem in some stories
in the גמרא, Gemara. it actually seems that that's okay,
although there's one particular passage in the גמרא Gemara that sounds like
you can only go up and you can't stay even. So that's
a big unanswered question that the ראשונים deal with. And the last
line here is וכן במותריהן, vechen bemotreihen, which is Michael's question. Any
leftover money also has to go to the same purpose. So even
if you went ahead and you sold your תיבה and you bought
מטפחות and you had a thousand dollars left over, you have to
use that leftover money for other things that you'll use in the
future for going up. You can't say that oh it's just the
difference and then I can apply the difference to something else. What?
You can't declare a dividend.
Exactly. Certainly not. Yes.
There's a lack of flexibility here. I mean I don't know over
the centuries obviously there've been all kinds of different
modes in which Jewish communities have to move or whatever and I
wonder if the context of the of the בבלי Bavli
or the משנה was different.
So that's a good point.
To have all these restrictions
assumes a
great deal of stability. We will see in the בבלי Bavli and
it actually introduces ברייתות, braitot, so it's not just in the
time of the גמרא, Gemara. that there are outs to this. There
are ways in which you can actually if you have enough of
the community behind it,
you can actually have a lot more latitude of what you do.
But it's a good point, even lay this type down certainly assumes
a great deal of stability.
Let's look at the תוספתא Tosefta and the בבלי.
Bavli. I'd have to look, I don't remember offhand, but that's a
very good question. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. בני עיר שמכרו רחובה של עיר אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן זו דברי רבי מנחם בר יוסי סתומא. bnei ir
shemachru rechovah shel ir amar Rabbah bar bar Channah amar Rabbi Yochanan
zu divrei Rabbi Menachem bar Yosi stuma. This סתמתא, setamta, this is
the סתם setam author of our משנה is רבי מנחם בר רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yosi. Now where does he get that
from? So רש"י Rashi tells you it's an explicit תוספתא Tosefta where
he says exactly this, רבי מנחם בר יוסי. Rabbi Menachem bar Yosi.
וחכמים אומרים הרחוב אין בו משום קדושה. veChachamim omrim harechov ein bo
mishum kedusha.
The public square has no קדושה. And here you get explicitly right.
The משנה did not say the word קדושה, it just said you
go up, you don't go down. It didn't say the word קדושה,
but that's clearly going to be the theme of all of this
in the way the גמרא Gemara understands it. And the city does
not have any קדושה, I'm saying the, the public square. רבי מנחם
ברבי יוסי מאי טעמא, Rabbi Menachem b'reibi Yosi mai ta'ama, why does
he say it does? הואיל ומתפללין בו בתעניות ובמעמדות, Hoil umitpallelin bo
b'ta'aniyot uv'ma'amadot, as we learned the people דאוון daven in it in
the תעניות Ta'aniyot and the מעמדות. Ma'amadot. Now מעמדות Ma'amadot is questionable
because there's no evidence that in the מעמדות Ma'amadot they דאוון daven
in the square. תוספות Tosafot crosses off the word. The רמב"ן Ramban
says it was just thrown in because תעניות Ta'aniyot ו u מעמדות
Ma'amadot usually go together. רש"י Rashi tries to find a way in
which people who came gathered together for the מעמדות Ma'amadot would sleep
in the public square. Anyway, the real focus is the תעניות. Ta'aniyot.
Since you would go there in the תענית and have this public
prayer, רבנן Rabbanan and the rabbis would say back, הוא קרא בעלמא,
hu kara b'alma, that's not really its identity. So once in a
blue moon you use it for public prayer, that doesn't mean that
it has קדושה, that doesn't give it any particular status. Okay, which
is an again an interesting question, right, if things' identity and what
happens when they're used occasionally for certain purposes and so on. בית
הכנסת לוקחין תיבה, lokchin teiva, if you sell the שול shul. you
can buy an ark, or a בימה I should say rather. אמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yonatan, לא שנו אלא בית הכנסת של כפרים, lo shanu
ela Beis Hakneset shel kfarim, and here we get to the interesting
question of who owns it. This is only true by a שול
shul of the villagers, אבל בית הכנסת של כרכים, aval Beis Hakneset
shel krachim, or by a שול shul, of a large city, כיון
דמעלמא אתו ליה, kevan d'mei'alma asu lei, since people come, you know,
a lot of people go to the big cities, right? I mean
you always have people coming from outside the city. So people come
to the city from outside, לא מצו מזבנו ליה, lo matzei mazvinu
lei, the people cannot sell it. Why? דהוי ליה דרבים, d'havei lei
d'rabbim, because it really does not belong to the city, it belongs
to the broader community, the masses. Now, interesting question. What does that
mean? Just because, right, so you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
there are two basic interpretations in the ראשונים. One is if it's
used by the masses we assume that they also are contributors to
it, on an interesting in terms of what we find in various
inscriptions in ancient synagogues about also like, you know, very חשוב chashuv
dignitaries and politicians whatever contributing to the synagogues. And the other question
is maybe even if they didn't contribute to it, but maybe it
was just made to serve them and that actually makes them part
owners. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, כיון דמעלמא
אתו ליה, kevan d'mei'alma asu lei, נראה לפרש הכי, neera lefaresh hachi,
כיון דרוב בני אדם רגילין ללכת שם להתפלל, kevan d'rov bnei adam
regilin lalechet sham l'hitpallel, אף על פי שאין נותנים כלום בבנינו, af
al pi she'ein notnim klum b'vinyano, since, you know, a majority of
people go there to דאוון daven even if they haven't contributed at
all, like everybody who goes to a שול shul and nobody decides
to become a member, right? מכל מקום כיון דלדעת אותן רבים נעשה,
Mikol makom kevan d'ledat otan rabbim na'aseh, חמור קדושתו ואין יכולים למכרו.
chamur kedushato v'ein yacholim l'mochro. So that just goes to show you
no good deed goes unpunished, right? Since you knew that it was
going to be coming from people all around, not necessarily people who
live in Manhattan, right? Everybody דאוונס davens in this שול, shul, so
it was made for them in mind and therefore they are considered
like part owners of it. Like if you think about a board,
right, the board of a שול, shul, you know, which has the
rights of it isn't because they necessarily have a, the people themselves
have made a monetary contribution to the שול. shul So presumably the
owners here are understood not necessarily in the sense of who paid
for it, but whose שול shul is it in the practical de
facto type of a sense, or for whom it was made. What
you say?
Good like rabbis.
So עוד יש לפרש, od yesh lefaresh, you could also explain, כיון
דרבים נותנים בבנינו ובצרכיו. kevan d'rabbim notnim b'vinyano uv'tzorchei. No, the assumption
is is that it's only because people other outsiders contribute to it
and therefore it's considered to be owned by everyone and not just
by the city. So let's take a look back in the גמרא.
Gemara, Even if someone doesn't like physically
own it, ah, so let's take a look at the next story
of the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, האי בי כנישתא דמתא מחסיא, hai bei knishta
d'Mata Mechasya, the synagogue in מתא מחסיא, Mata Mechasya, אף על גב
דמעלמא אתו ליה, af al gav d'mei'alma asu lei, even though people
come from outside of the city and דאוון daven in it, we
get a lot of outsiders in the שול, shul כיון דאדעתא דידי
קא אתו, kevan d'adaata d'didi ka'atu, they're coming because of me. I'm
the, you know, I'm the person in the שול shul that they
all are want to come. So there here we actually have a
case where the rabbi was a central figure in the שול, shul,
also questioned about בבל Bavel versus ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Anyway, here
he says they're all coming not because of the שול, shul they're
coming because of me. So אי בעינא מזבננא לה, i ba'ina mazvinna
lah, if I want to I can sell it. Okay, so what
does that mean? Does it mean that I'm a private owner and
therefore I did not, you know, it's not a case where they
actually contributed to it monetarily even though they visited? Does it mean
that even if they did contribute to it and so on, you
know, I in the end, since they sort of see me as
the, you know, as the, I'm seen as the person whose שול
shul. it is? So implicitly they sort of, you know, the same
way we can implicitly have owners of the רבים rabbim even if
nobody contributed because it's made for them, this type of place is
made with understanding that רב אשי, Rav Ashi, said who it was?
רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
That רב אשי, Rav Ashi, was, it was made for him, ultimately
it's his שול shul to do with it what he wants. Again,
not exactly clear here how ownership is is being defined. Again, doesn't
necessarily mean he owns it, right, but it might mean that he's
the one that's empowered to make the decisions, and the same as
the שול shul of the רבים. rabbim. They might not contribute to
it, but if it's made for them, they're the ones that are
possibly empowered to make the decisions.
Right, sort of authority as opposed to ownership because they're the ones
who because there are significant limitations on use of proceeds in any
event.
Exactly, exactly. So the idea of a board is a good is
a good parallel, right? A board can't sell a שול shul. and
pocket the money, right? They just have the dis- they're just empowered
to decide what to do with it. So exactly that. So you
might have רבים Rabbim or רב אשי Rav Ashi being the authorities
without the ones that actually have contributed, and that seems
to be what what if the person owns it? I can own
I can own the שול, shul, let the rabbi all right, you
know, like someone builds a שול shul, then you bring in a
rabbi and you get a whole קהילה kehillah right?
Right. So that's true, that's true. None of these have yet dealt
with a case of a really privately owned שול. shul. Okay. So
let's take a look. מתיבי, Meisive, I'll ask you on this. אמר
רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: מעשה בבית הכנסת של טרסיים Maiseh Beveish
Haknesses Shel Torsiyim and now maybe we'll get something closer to that.
There's a story of the synagogue of
Coppersmiths שהיה בירושלים, shehayah birushalayim, right? What do they have there like
in the the city? They have the garment workers' synagogue or whatever,
right? You have these like little guild שולס, right?
שהיה בירושלים shehayah birushalayim שמכרו לרבי אליעזר. shemacharu lerabbi eliezer. They sold
it to Rabbi Eliezer ועשאה בכל צרכו. veasasah bokol tzorcho. And he
did what he wanted to. So first of all you have the
question of using a שול once it was sold for other purposes,
which is what we'll get to in a later discussion although keeps
on intruding here. But the other thing you get is that here
it was in a city, it was in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. והתנן Vehasnan
דכרכים הוי, dekrachim havei, it was in a city, and how could
it be that they sold? You're not supposed to be empowered to
sell it if you're in a city, it's supposed to be owned
by everyone. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, ההיא בי כנישתא זוטא
הוה. hahi beiknishta zuta hava. That was a a small little שול
דאינהו עבדוה, deinhu avduah, they did it. So it wasn't really a
public שול. So what does that mean? Does it mean like Michael
said that it was seen as a private venture with a very
small group that contributed? Does it mean nobody else came to it?
Or does it mean even when other people came to it it
was still very much seen in a private sense as opposed to
a public sense? Right, because if you have a small group of
people and they made a small little שול, even when someone's visiting
they don't feel that, you know, it doesn't have the sense of
a public שול, it's someone visiting a private שול. So again, interesting
questions of its identity and is it all focus a question of
like who paid for it or who owns it or how it's-
how it's sort of, you know, how it's seen as private or
as public. All right, so now the גמרא, Gemara you know, goes
on. מתיבי, Meisive, I'll ask you, this idea that if it's considered
to be pub- that a synagogue in a in a city is
considered to be a public, you know, good or a public whatever,
you know, publicly owned. בבית ארץ אחוזתכם. Beveis eretz achuzaschem. It says
I will give צרעת tzara'as in a house of your land of
inheritance.
אחוזתכם מטמא בנגעים ואין ירושלים מטמא בנגעים. Achuzaschem mitamei bingaim veein Yerushalayim
mitamei bingaim. Only places that are really inherited meaning divided up by
the tribes
are can become טמא בנגעים, tamei bingaim, but ירושלים Yerushalayim it sort
of sees as a capital city and therefore not owned by any
particular tribe and therefore you don't have an אחוזה achuza in it
and the houses do not become טמא בנגעים. tamei bingaim. אמר רבי
יהודה: Amar Rabbi Yehuda:
אני לא שמעתי אלא למקום מקדש בלבד. Ani lo shamati ela limkom
mikdash bilvad. No, ירושלים Yerushalayim is מטמא- mitamei the houses are מטמא
בנגעים, mitamei bingaim, but there's one thing that is public and that
is not seen as private property, that would be the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, not the whole city of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the גמרא
Gemara says: הא בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות? Ha batei knesset ubatei midrashot?
According to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who feels ירושלים Yerushalayim is private property and
only the מקדש Mikdash is public property, presumably only the מקדש. Mikdash.
But synagogues and and study halls, interesting, we're going to get to
the study hall discussion, we haven't ex- first we're hearing about that.
מטמאין, mitamin, would become טמא, tamei, it is considered private. אמאי, Amai,
why? How does this fit with your argument? הא דכרכים הוי, Ha
dekrachim havei, that's part of a city and therefore something like a
synagogue should be considered public. So אימא, eima, all right, you have
to re- switch the words. אמר רבי יהודה: Amar Rabbi Yehuda: אני
לא שמעתי אלא למקום מקודש בלבד. Ani lo shamati ela limkom mekudash
bilvad. So not only מקום מקדש makom mikdash which is really the
one place the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, we're going to say sanctified
places. Places like בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, synagogues, בתי, batei, you know,
בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So that's quite a a re-read of רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. All right, anyway, so there is some evidence, right?
The גמרא is insisting because of this statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan that that in cities it's different, it's publicly owned, but a
lot of evidence is pointing against him, but the גמרא is continuing
to insist about this idea that in cities it is considered publicly
owned and you do not have rights to to sell it.
במאי קמיפלגי? Bimay kamifligi? Now getting back to this debate of can
ha- what's the status of Jerusalem? So what do they argue? תנא
קמא סבר לא נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים. Tanna Kamma savar lo nis'chalika Yerushalayim
lishvatim. ירושלים Yerushalayim was never divided and given into one שבט'ס נחלה.
shevet's nachala. It's owned by the entire people and it's not in
one שבט. shevet. רבי יהודה סבר נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים. Rabbi Yehuda savar
nis'chalika Yerushalayim lishvatim. It was in one שבט'ס נחלה. shevet's nachala. ובפלוגתא
דהני תנאי Ubiplukta dehanni tanna'ei which reflects the following debate of תנאים.
Tanna'im. דתניא Ditanya in a ברייתא: Baraita: מה היה בחלקו של יהודה?
Mah hayah bechelko shel Yehuda? What fell in the portion of יהודה?
Yehuda? הר הבית, Har Habayis, the Temple Mount, הלשכות והעזרות, halishkot veha'azarot,
the chambers and the עזרות. azarot. עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, עזרת נשים,
Ezrat Nashim, עזרת כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. ומה היה בחלקו של בנימין? U’mah
haya b’chelko shel Binyamin? What was in Benjamin’s חלק? chelek? Because בנימין
Binyamin and יהודה, Yehuda, they are sort of portion split in down
the middle of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? ירושלים Yerushalayim was split between the
two portions and the split happened on הר הבית. Har Habayis. So
what was in בנימין’ס Binyamin’s portion? אולם והיכל ובית קדשי קדשים. Ulam
v'haheichal u'veis kodesh hakodashim. The אולם, ulam, the room before, you know,
the basically to give you an idea here, there you have your
הר הבית, Har Habayis, okay, here you have your בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, your בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash sort of anyway, well we’ll do
it two-dimensional, what happened all of a sudden my markers stopped working
again. Anyway, okay, so here you have the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim,
right, here you’ve got this sort of came sort of around and
you have the various לשכות lishkaot around here. Here you’ve got the
עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, right, then you’ve got the sort of you
know עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim here, here’s the מזבח, mizbeach, right, and
then there’s the אולם, ulam,
the היכל, heichal, right, and the דביר, d'vir, right? So there you
go. Anyway, up I got the, I got the best first.
Anyway. Okay. Okay. So basically יהודה Yehuda gets, you know, the עזרות,
azarot, right, this area, the הר הבית, Har Habayis, okay, the עזרות,
azarot, right, and בנימין Binyamin gets the אולם, ulam, the היכל, heichal,
and the דביר. d'vir. What about the place smack in the middle
where you’ve got the מזבח? mizbeach? So let’s take a look. So
it says,
okay, ורצועה היתה יוצאה מחלקו של יהודה ונכנסת בחלקו של בנימין, u’retzuah
hayeta yotzei me’chelko shel Yehuda v’nichneset b’chelko shel Binyamin, and one strip
came out of יהודה’ס Yehuda’s portion and went into בנימין’ס Binyamin’s portion,
ובה מזבח בנוי, u’vah mizbeach banui,
and the altar was built on it. Now according to other sources,
it makes it sound like he got the whole מזבח, mizbeach, but
according to other sources, יהודה Yehuda only got like like this side
of the מזבח, mizbeach, like a little bit of the east side
or maybe even the east corner of the מזבח, mizbeach, and actually
that’s why there was not a יסוד, yesod, there was not the
final protrusion at the very bottom on the east side because the
idea was the מזבח mizbeach all ought to be in בנימין’ס Binyamin’s
חלק. chelek. So יהודה Yehuda got like right up to the מזבח,
mizbeach, cutting into the ground it would be in, right, a little
a little bit of a strip. Okay. והיה בנימין הצדיק מצטער עליה
בכל יום,
V’haya Binyamin hatzaddik mitztayer
aleha be’chol yom,
and every day בנימין Binyamin would be anguished over the fact that
he would not have the whole space of the מזבח. mizbeach. לבולעה,
L’vol’ah,
he wanted to swallow it, he wanted to absorb it into his
portion, שנאמר, shene’emar, as it says, חופף עליו כל היום, chofef alav
kol hayom, hovering over it the whole day.
לפיכך, Lefikach, because he was so desirous to have it, you know,
the the מזבח mizbeach in his portion, זכה בנימין ונעשה אושפיזיכין לשכינה.
zacha Binyamin v’na’asah ushpizchin lash’china.
בנימין Binyamin merited and became the sort of you know the host
of the שכינה Shechina because the קדשי קדשים Kodesh Hakodashim was in
his portion. Okay, so that’s all fascinating thing that could be completely
unpack, you could yeah do a lot of unpacking of that. But
anyway, it was
נתחלקה לשבטים. nitchalkah l’shvatim. והאי תנא סבר V’hai tanna savar לא נתחלקה
ירושלים לשבטים. lo nitchalkah Yerushalayim l’shvatim. It wasn’t divided by the tribes.
דתניא בברייתא: Detanya bivraita: אין משכירין בתים בירושלים מפני שאינם שלהם. en
maskirin batim b’Yerushalayim mipnei she’eiman shelahem.
People cannot rent out houses in ירושלים Yerushalayim to the visitors on
the רגלים regalim because in the end they’re not really the owners.
Now I gotta tell you that’s not necessarily assumed by נתחלקה לשבטים.
nitchalkah l’shvatim. לא נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים Lo nitchalkah Yerushalayim l’shvatim doesn’t mean
there’s no such thing as private ownership. Could be that there’s private
ownership but it doesn’t belong in any one particular שבט’ס shevet’s portion.
This is going even further with this idea of like you know
the sense of like the בית הכנסת which is owned by the
רבים. rabbim. So it’s not just it’s not one person’s, there’s not
even real private ownership. All of ירושלים Yerushalayim is owned by all
of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. And if you happen to own a
house, you’re not really owning a house, you’re really I don’t know
renting it in perpetuity from כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. But really it’s
all you don’t no private ownership in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It’s all owned
by כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. So therefore when כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
comes up for the רגל, regel, you’re not allowed to charge. It’s
כלל ישראל’ס Klal Yisrael’s houses and there’s an assumption that you don't
own it, you know, you don't have rights to prevent people from
staying in your house when they’re עולה לרגל. oleh l’regel. Yes. Yes.
Yes.
Well for this concept of dividing ירושלים, Jerusalem,
does it have economic implications?
Well yes, here’s what we were just saying, that’s what I said
until this line you would have thought that it
right, but at the יובל yovel level.
Oh, well yeah, for issues like יובל, yovel, right? I mean you
know and how things are חוזר ביובל, chozer b’yovel, so if it
belonged to a שבט shevet then it all sort of goes back.
If this is even if there were private ownership if it was
לא נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים lo nitchalkah Yerushalayim l’shvatim I don't think you'd
have the whole ideas of יובל yovel which are ultimately based on
that like original נחלה nachala and the identity of the שבט shevet
and so on.
But they were suggesting that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the
מזבח mizbeach and so on were private property.
According to the first opinion. Now we're at the position of לא
נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים, lo nitchalkah Yerushalayim l’shvatim, that's the debate, right? But
yeah but the גמרא does seem to take this to the point
that it's not just about שבטים shvatim but it's about no private
ownership. Let's just read one more line and end with that. רבי
אליעזר בר צדוק אומר: Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok omer: אף לא מטות,
af lo mitot, you can’t even rent them beds. Okay, I’m not
going to rate you for the room but I’ll charge you for
the bed. The bed is mine, the bed is right is chattel,
it's not real estate. So he says no you can’t even. for
the bed. Why? Because whose property is the bed on, right? So
you don't have real rights to charge me for the bed. I'm
not taking the bed out and carrying it on my back, you
know? So it's here sitting on this ground. This ground is my
ground too, so you can't really charge me for the bed.
ולפיכך, U'l'fichach, but therefore can't charge him for anything, right?
All right. Well, then if he can't charge him for anything, עורות
קדשים בעלי אושפיזין נוטלין אותן בזרוע. Orot kodashim ba’alei ushpizin notlin otan
b’zroa. That when you go to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you bring your
קרבן, korban, you're left with over, what are you left with? The
skin of the animal, which is leather, which is very expensive. So
basically I can say okay fine, you're not getting charged, but you're
leaving me the skin of your קרבנות, korbanot, the leather of your
קרבנות, korbanot, and therefore you can even forcibly demand that gift. We're
not going to leave the owners completely without any compensation. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, שמע מינה, sh'ma mina, we hear from
this, אורח ארעא למישבק איניש גופא ומשכא באושפיזיה. orech ara l'mishbak inish
gufa umshcha b'ushpizeih. We hear from this that it's courtesy for a
person to leave like, you know, leather and a jug in his,
in you know, in the host house as opposed to our practice,
not ours, people's practice, which is that you take like the robe
from the hotel room. Here you leave your robe and you leave
your stuff in the hotel room. Okay, to be continued tomorrow.